okay
uh who's on the is that
chlo some number
two yeah okay you guys
ready okay calm
down they're so excited to sleep through
my class
uh okay
tum uh turam gum is the tradition
way to do Dharma means classroom time
okay listening in Sanskrit uh it means
classroom hours and a lot of people
think you don't need classroom
hours uh to do Dharma and it's a it's
very mistaken okay you need as many
hours as you can do you have to sit
there even if you're half
asleep it's it's even better cuz it's
like
hypnosis
and okay so uh you know classroom hours
Buddha said you need classroom hours the
more hours you can sit in here the the
better your life is going to be and and
I'm how do you
say uh I spent my whole life sitting in
my llamas classes and uh and I'm very
happy super happy and I I believe it's
very fun and I believe it's going to
change your whole life so don't be lazy
about it just do it okay you don't have
to be super genius and you don't have to
listen very
carefully but just be there okay to some
means think about it when you go home
when I think of some I think of time in
my
car uh so it's just time usually I'm
alone I'm
driving and I'm just thinking about
things and that's some that's typical
some that's about the only time I can be
alone and think about things uh so and
then g means formal meditation so t
means hear hear about the
Dharma Sam means think about it when
you're alone or you're I don't know I
have a special room in my
house right I I do this
um my my wife says you know other people
also have to poop you know and I'm like
all right you know she said you've been
in there for 45 minutes I'm like okay
that's a good place to contemplate and
then is meditation
okay CH ro ro is the important word here
say
Ro so ro means uh taste the taste of
something means to experience the taste
of something so he says you have to
learn to experience the taste of the
Dharma okay and what's it
mean we tend to have
Colo what's that backwards we tend to
enjoy the taste of things that are not
going to help us okay and I think that
internet is the ultimate example I think
your phone is the ultimate example okay
and uh it's it's
tasty it it's attractive you know I also
enjoy reading three different versions
of today's news you know and uh I don't
know why uh I also enjoy it and if I
don't get it I feel like I'm missing
something you know so he says uh get
your taste what do you call it taste
enjoyment do it with the right things do
your taste enjoyment which is a good
time Lindsay to talk
about so during the pandemic I I got uh
more and more into my uh phone it
actually happened with the last
presidential election in the United
States and I was very worried about it
and uh I remember even sitting in Gil's
out house and following the electoral
vote and uh you know and I started to
read the the the news on my phone uh I
never did it before that I had friends
who did it and I thought they were
stupid and uh then I started to do it
and um then it was
okay uh and uh so I I don't know I kept
reading then I started reading more and
more then I start watching movies then I
start watching Korea soap opera
which are really
good and uh then I start watching war
movies then I start watch all kinds of
bad movies and and uh then I got real
addiction and I was doing it late at
night like I'll wake up at 2 o'clock and
I can't sleep and I say I'll go I'll go
eat some food in the refrigerator and uh
and watch part of a movie and it got
worse and worse and then uh I have a
friend uh
presscut will Duncan who who was a
student here and he said uh he has a
small Retreat Center I think he does two
or three people come there for the
weekend and he takes away your
phone at 9 o'l or something and he locks
it you know and then we were talking
about it he was telling me about it and
I and I kept thinking I would like to
try it so I started uh this thing called
good night book
club and uh you promised to give up your
electronics that I say 10 o'clock when
I'm here I do nine because I get up
earlier so but I do 10 o'clock I put
away my computer I put away my phone I
put them in a drawer and then at 2
o'clock I get up and open the drawer
and and then I realized I cannot have it
in the house you know uh
so actually Rob comes to my house uh he
lives near me he picks up my computer
and my phone at 10 o' he brings it back
at 6
o'clock and when I'm at Diamond Mountain
he comes and gets it here and if I'm
traveling or
something uh I have to add the TV
controller from the hotel
room and uh then he found out there's
two in my
room and
but uh now it's a good I I I I put
everything away we have a special bag
Lindsay's in charge of this project we
stand up
[Applause]
yeah and uh she has we have
Representatives around the world in this
one of the
representatives Olga
Olga where's
Olga yeah Olga is another one Mr Ben is
another one
[Applause]
uh so if you're in Europe or the US you
talk to yeah Ina if you're in Latin
America you talk to oga if you're in
Vietnam you talk to Mr bin if you're in
I don't know that it oh China you talk
to Tina
L uh Pacific Rim you talk to suang sh or
his wife
shinten and um you can sign up for this
and
Rosa so I have a charity where I sell
jewelry and I sell expensive things and
we give the money we give the profit
after paying our staff and
taxes uh we give the profit to the
country where we sold the stuff so like
if we sell jewelry in China we donate
the money to a project to help save the
books at dun Hong in Vietnam we Mr Ben
has built over 800 homes for poor people
yeah and
[Applause]
uh so we give the money uh locally so we
uh we made a fancy uh valis case uh it
has a lock on it it has a time lock on
it and you can set the lock for 10 10
p.m. and 6 a.m. and I always wanted to
get up early you know everybody thought
I got up early but I didn't and uh you
know I just struggle to get up at 7 or 8
o' or something like I don't I didn't
get up early for since my three-year
Retreat I don't think I got up early
and so now I go to bed at 10:00 I go get
up at 6 and I can and that's how I
finish s's book it's 800 pages and uh I
had time you know I had time to focus
and do my practice so um I really really
really uh encourage you to uh to join
this book club and uh there's a joke Mr
Ben it's called good night book club
then when Lindsay's in a rush she says
good night club and then everybody says
nightclub gu I started at n
Club I said no it's a good night book
club everybody's like I'll
join maybe we should start a nightclub
Mr B uh anyway uh so and I never slept
so well in my whole life I never slept
for eight hours in my whole life and uh
I sleep eight hours and I feel wonderful
and I meditate
really so
[Laughter]
oh yeah that's what Rob gets every
night so I really encourage you to do it
and that's rang Rony Yang means uh enjoy
the taste of the Dharma don't Goo Goo
means uh you get addicted to the taste
of news or sports or you know stupid
things uh movies a good movie once in a
while is a Dharma practice
uh but a good movie twice or three times
a day is not a Dharma
practice so be sensible you know it's
good to
relax and I enjoy good movies and and I
if I'm really tired I watch one but I
don't I'm not addicted to it okay so he
says you should be addicted to
Dharma and that's R okay but don't be
addicted to news here it's called jangi
song means uh talking about business or
it's good to do business it's so so good
to make your own money and not grub off
of other grub
means you just borrow money from other
people or you're always taking money
from other people it's good to be
independent financially and have your
own
money uh but don't go crazy and and do
business 12 148 18 hours a day okay
because you will die and uh so do do a
good business uh work hard
enjoy have fun uh but don't let it take
over your whole life okay and then Mar
so Mo so means talking about uh current
events Mark Means War and and sometimes
we just get into reading about the war
we don't intend to help about it we
don't we don't want to help we're just
addicted to reading about it so he says
try to get addicted to your good night
book club
practice and don't get addicted to these
other things okay addiction is good if
it's the right thing okay all right
that's number two don't do backwards
addiction okay there's an English
expression ask backwards completely
opposite okay number three
[Music]
or go then he says uh backwards
compassion and he says uh we should have
compassion for dien dien
means people who are doing bad things
okay we should have compassion for them
the people who are organizing these wars
who are promoting these wars uh who
think that killing people and taking
their property is is going to give them
more property it's crazy it's insane uh
so we should have compassion for those
people and we should real compassion you
know not where you just hate them but
you don't say you hate them or something
like that but but you're like wow these
people are really messed up you know
these people are really sad and uh be
compassionate for them okay the ones who
are organizing these violence and stuff
like that uh
CH then he says we tend to somebody says
oh you know John Brady and they took
their group to Turkey and they Maria and
Peter and then they're stuck in that
hotel meditating all day poor guys they
should go to Paris they did go to Paris
and they didn't take me either
anyway uh so he says don't have
compassion for the wrong people
okay you should not have compassion for
John Brady and Peter and Maria who are
stuck in retreat in Turkey are you doing
it again this year when October October
don't forget to take your friends if
you're go to Paris okay uh it's a
wonderful retreat but we tend to have
compassion for all these poor guys at
Diamond Mountain poor cats stuck in a
retreat cabin all
year you you should have compassion for
the other people who are not in a
retreat Kevin okay and okay number
four
means
aspiration what do you want okay what do
you dream about okay col means what yeah
ask backwards don't don't have wrong
dreams okay what's the dreams he says
you should dream about being an
excellent Dharma practitioner you know
do you have a regular meditation yes did
you join the good night book club yes do
you actually sleep all night yes you
know do you look at the news no uh do
you meditate in the morning yes do you
read your Dharma book the best way to go
to sleep is to read a Dharma book okay
Ma
M excellent okay you won't last six
minutes
okay we tell people lock up your
electronics get one of those books and
try to read two pages and you
go completely asleep okay so dream about
all the cool practices by the way
nobody's perfect you're going to your
practice collapses every six months okay
if your practice doesn't collapse every
6 months it means you're not
practicing okay the only way to not have
your practice collapse every six months
is don't practice at all okay so if you
have your practice collapsed every six
months you should be proud of it why
because you have a practice to collapse
okay so you know once you've been doing
this for couple years you you notice a
pattern okay you don't go like this okay
figure learn you go like this wow wow
wow boom wow wow wow boom wow wow wow
boom so it's like this it's not Dharma
doesn't go like that I'm sorry for
nobody not for bua it goes like
this and you just try to get a little
higher
collapse we should write a book Maria
the higher collapse
go like that
[Music]
okay don't dream about money and
position and the
best way to ruin your Dharma practice is
to dream about being a famous Dharma
practitioner you know then you really
ruin your Dharma
practice so like that okay number five
means how do you
say d means uh what are your goals what
are your ultimate goals okay Cog
means backwards yeah uh say
cha cha first first line here cha
that's the definition of taking
Refuge okay that's the definition of
taking Refuge if if you know philosophy
if you if you did the gashi course R
chawa is the ancient ancient word R
chawa means put all your hopes in
somebody you know who's going to help me
then you put all your hopes in in some
person by the way some of the words in
tibetan are not some of the letters are
not pronounced like this L here is not
pronounced the S is not pronounced so
get used to it R Jaa means you put all
your hopes in who do you put all your
hopes in you know who do you put your
hopes in and and it should be
somebody who
can uh manage a whole
universe okay there's people who can
manage not a whole planet a the whole
universe people who can walk from planet
to planet in a in a few hours okay those
are the kind of people you should put
your hopes in okay don't put your hopes
in in little powerful people okay talk
think about the big ones the people who
walk through the universe from planet to
planet and who can help billions of
people at the same time okay put your
hope in
the put your hope in really amazing
people and there are people like that
okay there are people like that there
are people close to us who have walked
the
planets okay uh you put your hope in
those people don't don't say oh this guy
oh look his Tesla company's 12% up today
yeah and it's 18% up down next week you
know you know don't that poor
guy I mean it's better not to make $18
billion and lose it the next week or 800
I don't know okay to Cha Chim P
CH if people put their hopes in
you then do something for them which is
Big okay don't like you know give them
some few dollars and stuff like that you
know oh look G is so kind what he gave
me a used car you know uh uh that's
not that's not fulfilling people's hopes
give them some hope
for future lives next lives okay I'm
looking at Alex
realas uh me and Alex have a
project uh he he he said let's do a
project and I'm like yeah okay what is
it and uh we decided there's too much
war in the world and one of the things
we could do about it is to help
children uh understand how bad is war so
uh so Alex agreed to go to elementary
schools in Mexico where he lives and he
went to teachers and and
students and we asked them to
write uh a suggestion how to stop War
and we asked the people who still have a
clear mind which is under 10 years old
can we say uh so we got all these
answers uh from the mouth of babes we
call from the mouth of children uh we
got all these suggestions from children
in
Mexico uh of how to stop
war and uh the problem is Alex sent them
to me I can't read them
uh cuz they're in
Spanish so I brought them to Diamond
Mountain so look at they're so cute um
so Alex can read them to us sometime
okay so
uh than
you and uh they say kids have let's find
a time but they say kids have a more
clear mind say stop doing this and
you're like duh that's what we should do
so if you're
interested uh you can sit with Alex or
or other other guys from guara and and
read them together and thank you for
doing that
[Applause]
Alex I think we bribed them didn't we
bribe them did we bribe them we bribed
them
we gave him a little moer
okay all
right okay uh number six what are these
six yeah backwards
yeah what's
y y means to celebrate another person's
Good Deeds or something like that it's
one of
the
Georgia right is
it number
four yeah celebrate other people's good
stuff okay and he says uh celebrate the
good things that other people do c you
know like this thing where without we
just did a rang okay it means celebrate
what people do which is nice
and don't
celebrate people mess up okay and he
says our tendency is to mess up is to be
celebrate when other people mess up we
he we hear oh did you hear this person
got a divorce or did you hear this
person had a big fight or you know like
that okay we tend to celebrate we tend
to get interested in people's failures
rather than people's successes there are
politicians who fail
daily and the news is full of their news
you know and then the ones who do good
stuff we there's no news about them okay
so that's called
backwards interest in people's failure
okay all right
um here's a cute story in support of the
six colls
okay there was a great Gan named btoa in
the time of the kadambas about 900 years
ago and
uh he this G
heard that someone was
celebrating and he asked him what is he
celebrating and he said I heard that
this other
monk who I don't like did a PBA PBA is
one of the four most serious breaking
your vows uh as a like murdering
somebody and and then you lose your vows
immediately uh so he heard
his
enemy committed a PBA his enemy
committed a bad deed that would make him
lose his Monks f in a second you know
and he was so happy because the guy was
his enemy you know then this G kadami he
heard about it and he said you just
committed a PBA worse than the other
guy's PBA got it being
happy that someone else failed in their
vows
is worse than the guy who failed got it
okay rejoy you know celebrating that
someone else failed is worse than you
know failing itself okay and I think we
tend to do that with people we don't
like when we hear that they had some
trouble or they failed or you know uh
some guy you don't like in business then
they go bankrupt and then you're like
you're trying not to smile right and or
somebody at work that you're jealous of
and then they fail they get yelled at by
the boss and you're like oh I'm so sad
you know it's too bad you know so
there's this kind of backwards rejoicing
that other people failed and he
says the karma of that kind of enjoyment
is worse than the failure okay your
karma is worse than the other
guys if you want to
learn colloquial tan which is much
there's about three or four different
levels of Tibetan language it has
honorific form it has a high honorific
form it has an epistolary form for
writing letters it has U public forms it
has Dharma forms it has colloquial forms
if you want to learn to speak to
someone in everyday Tibetan this book is
the best in the world okay and there's
no book like
it uh colloquial Tibetan you know
Tibetan spoken between
friends is uh has no spelling
okay because nobody writes it but in
this book they do so you know if you
have an AI project we have an AI project
I'll tell you about uh you can teach it
to colloquial to good colloquial to so
this book is unusual very highly
unusual so I want to teach you a word
okay say
it's in the first line
hereu okay uh Nung means uh what
renunciation okay uh oh I broke up with
my
girlfriend now I'm just gonna do Retreat
the rest of my life you know like that
this
Dharma what do you call
it temporary Dharma feeling you know uh
oh uh my my friend died of cancer now
I'm gonna get serious you know that's
called Nunu p means uh
Goosebump when you get cold like if you
have the bad luck to sit in front of the
air conditioner
here right you guys she got a jacket on
um by the way we designed it wrong I'm
sorry if you can do it better you're
welcome uh but uh the people in the
middle are hot and the people people in
the side are cold so the Goosebump when
you get
cold uh it's a famous colloquial Tibetan
expression
for shortterm
renunciation you know you're someone
Close to You dies of cancer then you
meditate really hard for three days and
then you're like God this is too hard
you know and the the sadness wears off
it means the sadness wears off okay and
then you get you get used to life again
you know somebody has it somebody
commits suicide yesterday then for two
days you feel very religious and then
then it wears off okay that's called PSU
Buu
means the bump comes up when you're cold
and it goes back down fast right so if
you want to make a joke to a tietan you
can say how's youru
it means your five minute renunciation
okay it's kind of an insult okay you
might not want to use
it
Yim Jim Jim means you focus you focus
really hard on your practice CH
means what's Cho you guys know it means
uh Fierce
Theory but with renunciation it means
you work really hard for like two
days and then you just get back to
normal okay so Jim Jo means you over
Focus
gor then Tim is hard to read you got to
say say listen
g
mij okay she got to read mij gu together
mij gu means every which
way okay you try a million things Goo
means nine into
but in in English we say uh somebody
close to you dies of cancer then for one
week you're doing like a million
meditations and then you get over it and
you forget meditation okay so mij means
you pull out like a million different
kind of
practices and then the person's gone for
a week and you start to forget about
them and then you you get back to normal
okay so mij gu means you get ah you get
real what do you call
it yeah you get all fired out you know
gu means you do everything you try
everything and then it wears off you
know even with your mother or something
when when your mother passes you have
mij gu for like six months and then even
that wears off okay
so Tang what's Tong anybody Tong Tong CH
means you get tired tongue chain
means this Dharma stuff I'm going back
to
Netflix you know t t if you're gonna
learn to speak to
B Tong CH is a very CH means to cut like
d
Chupa Diamond Cutter Sutra and tongue
means
your power tongue chain means oh man I
kicked gas for 6 months that's that's
probably enough and then you get tired
tongue CH then you go back to watching
movies and stuff like that
okay means you give up your Dharma
practice okay that's enough okay
temporary renunciation temporary
renunciation when someone Close to You
dies use the time use the chance because
it will wear off
it will wear off okay so when someone
Close to You leaves this
world uh use it use the time because it
will wear off you won't remember them
six months from now so okay all right
all right uh next picture you guys tune
it like a
guitar uh I'm going to read
the the Tibetan
here Ren is another colloquialism so
this book is full of you could write a
AI dictionary of colloquial Tibetan from
this book and it would be very
interesting Ren joke means hot hot and
cold you know you work hard then you
quit for six months and then you work
hard and then you quit Okay Ren joke
means you flip
flipflop okay Rena go L then he quotes
uh a llama who lived about 500 years
ago he
said okay and this is practice
advice everyday practice advice M gang
sing gang means distance sing means long
and he says keep your focus far ahead
okay like on your old age and your death
okay uh keep your me and my wife are at
this point where we discuss buying stuff
that probably we won't live to see it
finished you see what I mean we're like
buy something that's going to last 20
years we're like I don't know make young
thinging means look ahead you know don't
be stupid look look ahead keep your eyes
ahead look at what's coming okay in your
life you will get old uh you will lose
your energy you will die so keep your
eyes ahead don't get all hypnotized by
your last bonus or something it's not
going to last okay look keep your eyes
far ahead M thing y means think big
think big you know I'm gonna walk the
planets you know I'm GNA help a billion
people okay to think big don't think
about stopping the war in Ukraine or
Goda let's stop war on a billion planets
think big if you cover a billion planets
you also cover
Gaza okay
seriously so y means think
big think Big K Kong is is the important
one here say
Kong uh this Sr is just s l h is
HL and that means uh the picture of the
G
guitar yeah and this is a very common uh
L Rim example is tuning a
guitar and uh don't make it too tight
and don't make it too loose it means
don't make your practice too tight and
don't let your practice get too loose if
you're too tight and you're always
nervous about your practice your
practice to the point where your hands
are shaking it's too tight you're going
to mess up the string is going to break
okay don't tune your practice too tight
okay then you're going to be uptight and
you won't be able to meditate well so
don't don't go
crazy slow and steady wins the race
right just don't don't go crazy and try
to meditate 12 hours a day and it's not
going to
last okay what's a meditation teacher
advice with a new meditator
start with 10 minutes please please
please start with 10 minutes no gu I can
do two hours no you can't I can stay
still for two hours so can a
rabbit uh you know that was my teacher's
answer yeah they don't meditate they
just sit there you know
so okay so tune your practice also not
to lose
okay I'll tomorrow I'll meditate
tomorrow you know today I'm really busy
shut up sit down you know you're not
that
busy don't get into this Dharma
organizer trap you know oh I'm so busy
organizing meditation classes I don't
have time to meditate you know that's
what yoga teachers do once you become a
yoga teacher you're in
trouble because then you're like I have
to have a school have to organize the
classes I don't have time to do yoga
okay so don't get into
this to
to too not tidy no too loose tune the
guitar to the right sound okay practice
don't be all like nervous and don't get
lazy either keep the tuning correct it's
a very beautiful metaphor for your
meditation practice don't over meditate
and don't under meditate okay all
right so there's
the very very colloquial expression Tong
means too tight FL means too loose Rea
means just right okay re and you won't
see that word anywhere Tim for example
it's just it means just to the right
what do you call
it uh tension tension it's like a guitar
enough tension but not too much tension
okay I don't know what's nuk sing I got
to look it up okay sorry sing means it I
think it means be there for the long run
be there for the long run don't get too
tight don't get too lazy keep it going
for the long run nuk
sing now beautiful because the author of
this L Rim the speaker of this L rim is
one of the most amazing Diamond W
practitioners in history okay so this is
not a a basic
Elementary text this is a secret Diamond
way explosion manual you know and people
don't know that but but Pabon R
was maybe the greatest vaj guini
practitioner of all time his commentary
on vaju is used in the in our Diamond
way courses 18 courses the diamond way
course that diamond mountain started at
diamond mountain is the best in the
world that ever existed uh okay and you
will never see a course like that we
took the best of the best of the best
for the last 2,000 years and we made a
course out of it and it's amazing so
anyway d d Nour he's referring to vaj
guini practice secretly which is how you
should refer to
it uh what is
D what does vaj practice start
with sleep I like any practice that
starts with
sleep I'm on board
uh okay the first of the vaji yini
secret yogas is go to
bed I like it uh it means go to bed with
a special motivation and and go to bed
with special thoughts and then the
second of the great uh yogas of vaji
practice is dung which how do you wake
up how do you wake up as her you know
how do you get out of bed
you know got
it okay you don't just jump out of bed
you like do it slow and remember who you
are okay and you always put the correct
foot out first you don't like jump out
okay dang NJ means NJ means The Yoga of
uh waking okay so it's so beautiful in
the middle of alarm room he's at the end
of the alarm room
uh starting with your wake up routine
okay with your tantric wakeup routine
starting with your wakeup
routine get yourself ready for the day
okay in vaji yini practice it's a
whole getting your vision of yourself
ready for the day you know God is
getting out of bed God is making coffee
God is getting ready for work I mean if
you put it in Christian terms it's
something like that it's it's it's
radical and it's beautiful okay so start
R di get yourself set for the day are
you
divine not really I still sleepy okay
take a few minutes get it together don't
get out of bed until you're
Divine okay it's a beautiful idea
okay
CH start basic okay get your I don't
know step out with your left foot get
your
hair
right and then start adding stuff G may
start adding stuff okay when you eat
when you drink your coffee serve it to a
billion
Angels sitting in your heart okay then
start getting more what you call
it yeah like gong means that's the gay
and
S you know send it to the ends of the
universe okay by the time you have your
cereal I'm getting
hungry uh by the time you have your
cereal your practice should be totally
Divine okay then when you go to work no
problem bajin is going to work all right
uh
again extremely
colloquial and such a chain
means uh your practice will advance in
Leaps and Bounds so sat means you can
cover a million miles in 10
minutes sat means like a jet airplane
covering the miles as opposed to a horse
okay if your wake up motivation is
divine then sa before noon you've
covered a billion miles okay your
practice has gone a billion miles before
noon okay if you wake up with the right
vision of yourself okay and that's
Tantra that's Diamond way okay sat means
uh you can cover major ground before
noon okay such a CH uh then he says she
apparently there's some uh story intoon
about the race between the lice and the
flea the bed bug and the
flea fleas jump bed bugs
crawl if you don't know about it go to
India to
study you that was gross I mean my early
years in India when they sleep in the
beds they had wooden Mac beds string
beds no mattress wooden frame and the
bed bugs live in them and then uh they
come out and suck your blood at night
and they start out really small and they
get filled up with your blood and then
they're all full and they they hang on
to the wall and they're
like you know and then when you wake up
there's all these bed bugs on the wall
big red B balloons you know like if you
hit one by accident there's a blood goes
down the wall you're like
Anyway bed bugs move
slow uh fleas move fast so don't pet a
dog in India either because they jump on
you okay okay got it it means be like
the flee and don't be like the bed bug
okay make
progress make major progress every day
be a jet engine and don't be a horse
okay be like the flea that can jump a
half a meter or something and don't
don't be like a bed bug that has to
crawl around and wait for night to suck
okay like make
progress while you can and and Tantra is
the best way Diamond way is the best way
you know when you wake up like that
guini and you you do you do two hours
baj guini in the morning and the rest of
the day you have a
breakdown you're making Fast progress
okay okay it's better than just some
dull long Dharma day got it okay that's
Diamond wave practice all
right uh next
picture uh that's my wife's surgeon
and that's her new
knee and uh it's titanium my I always
knew my wife was
titanium uh so
uh you know I I was there unfortunately
and uh she her knee got worse and worse
and worse she's a athlete she's a runner
she's the fastest runner at her school
she beat all the boys that's why I
didn't go to her school uh
and uh then she wore out the cartilage
and they had to replace her knee and um
I was there me and Stanley and Allison
were there and they put you outside and
they say okay well you know I get to
hold her hand until they put the
drugs and then they say okay now you can
go outside and then I hear
this and I'm like oh my God and they're
cutting her bone off they're cutting the
edge of the bone off and then they drill
a
hole and then they like get a hammer and
they slam the knee in you know and you
can hear this bam bam you know I'm like
oh and uh and the the the surgeon this
is the assistant surgeon the surgeon
surgeon was uh Christian very strong
Christian and we liked him a lot we we
interviewed many surgeons and
uh and we said what's your experience he
said I had 10 years doing knes
in uh Uganda or
something as a volunteer for free he he
did 2,000 knes in Africa for 10 years
we're like we want you you and uh so he
came out and he and he and he said
uh okay we're ready to start and he said
do you mind if we do a prayer and I'm
like
and then he did a prayer and then it was
so
beautiful and then he said you go and he
then
he and he didn't hesitate he didn't uh
sit around and
go you know he's just like and cut her
leg open and that's what it's talking
about here okay so it's what do you call
it don't F
around like be decisive your practice
okay like when you start you start with
the circular
s you know don't go like oh you know
like you know when you jump into your
practice jump and don't don't hesitate
and don't be wimpy you know like when
it's time to cut cut and be be like
short be decisive and
cut d joh means uh cut through your
indecision don't be wimpy don't say I
think I want to meditate but I'm not
here you know like shut up and sit down
who you talking to
yourself shut up and sit down you know
we're gonna meditate don't
hesitate
J show your heart into
lojo don't don't hold back if you're
going to do this do do it
100% okay don't don't say maybe I want
to meditate and maybe I don't want to
meditate then shut up and don't meditate
and go
away okay
like you're gonna die you don't have
much time stop uh pooping around you
know go go for it okay l l l lingi is
another very very
very uh beautiful colloquial EXP
expression it means give it
100% give it 100% don't mess around
okay so in the
ancient medical system of Tibet um
tibet's unusual because
geographically is halfway between
Chinese traditional medicine ctm
and ayur vtic Medicine in India so
geographically it's between the two
places and the medical system of Tibet
is very very amazing because it they
took the best from India and they took
the best from Central China so um
Tibetan medicine is unbelievable and I
translated for a couple years for two of
the greatest doctors and um it's amazing
okay so he they they have a system of of
moxabustion
you you do acupuncture with a Golden
Needle it's called serup and then you
put Cotton On The Golden Needle and you
light it I it's really fun being the
translator because I saw these old Rich
New York ladies
going
and and uh so anyway you have to be
decisive when you're doing acupuncture
or when you're doing uh work with
people's bodies you can't be
indecisive you have to move with you
have to move with confidence okay you
have to say okay I might mess this up
but here we go and and then do it
with yeah like I can I can do this you
know and then don't be like oh maybe I
can do it maybe I can't okay so think
think means cut to the Bone in the First
Slice don't mess around
okay Tupa means uh let the bone and the
stone meet and it's again it's a very
very colloquial to Buton and it means uh
kick
ass okay let the bone and the stone
meet okay kick ass don't mess around
okay go for it don't D to say doru to do
means Stone like DJ means diamond right
Ru means bone to means let
them it's it's like let them smash into
each other you know let the
stone let the stone crash into the bone
it means throw your heart into it you
know go for it don't hold back go for it
okay with your practice okay don't hold
back Tim how's my
time 15
minutes
okay I'm not going to take questions in
the second session because we got to
cover some
ground we got to what do you call make
[Music]
progress
say so here it is if you learn the three
kinds of meditation what are they
sh Jo okay Shon means list
meditation go through a list you know
what are the seven preliminaries for
example and review them in your mind
with your eyes closed that's called shum
that's a good one to do before you go to
work in the
morning and I have very successful
business executives in Taiwan for
example uh who use it every morning they
do a uh they do a shome on what they're
going to they they walk through the day
before they go to work and they're
they're all when they get to work
they're all ready and they kick butt you
know so that's called Sho step by step
before you
go Cho means uh Take A question put it
at the center of your mind and work it
out
it's a problem solving meditation
Joo focused on one picture like a
llama's face or bini's face or put a put
a face in front of you and hold it and
and sink into it that's called Joo he
says here uh Cho do a problem solving
meditation about
meditation what's that mean
decide you know ask yourself in the
morning do you really want to spend this
much time
meditating why like uh interrogate
yourself Chom here means interrogate
your own heart you know are you going to
meditate yes why well I don't know guess
what I said to not good enough you know
give me some reasons you know give me
some good reasons why you're going to
Med debate yourself before you start
your meditation why you why are you
spending this time and then make sure
you have good answers before you start
meditating okay don't meditate because
it's a habit or your teacher said you
should do it or your friends are doing
it or something like that debate
yourself why why should I spend this
hour
meditating you know well I'm gonna die
right that's good you're on the right
track
okay got it
[Music]
okay this is a very uh nice advice by
the way this L Rim is the greatest book
of advises
ever I was having lunch with my wife's
mother and her boy her short-lived
boyfriend uh she was already 80
something and uh we were talking about
what's the greatest book ever written
you know she's of course Bible mom is
Bible but I'm like no it's it's this LM
it's Liberation in the Palm your hands
anyway it
says when you're deciding what to
meditate
on do a review of your negative emotions
and pick the worst
one okay review your
life review your personal psychology
identify your greatest weakness and go
for it okay so sh Shewa again Tim if
you're interested very colloquial sha
means what's the worst one okay which is
the fattest one go for that what's your
worst negativity go for that first
okay 10 means apply the anti uh okay
next picture binocular is franc
yeah uh Sam Jen keep doing
ding uh it
is
completely appropriate that you should
spend your hours of your short life
serving other people that's the best
thing you can do okay what's the best
way to
spend the extremely short short hours of
your life is help other people spend
your as many hours as you
can helping other people here means
means it's worth it that's the best way
to use your time you don't have many
minutes in this life the more you can
give to other people the better okay
good good job
okay simbe once you've agreed to help
other people
[Music]
people okay do you want to live the body
sest way of life yes do you promise to
try to be a bodh sera yes do you
understand it's serving other people yes
are you willing to serve other people
almost all day except for
snacks yes then shut up and don't expect
any thanks from anybody okay you me CH
means don't expect anybody to thank you
okay don't don't help people and then
stand around
like do you want to thank me or anything
and they're like
no okay as a b zaa get used to it okay
you you you kick ass you help other
people give them all your money give
them all your time and then they're like
could I just could you help me for one
more hour and you're like I just gave
you six months of my time and they're
like yeah but I have one more thing I
need and then don't expect people to
thank you okay if you're looking for
thanks you're in the wrong business okay
buddy s business is thank lless business
okay no one's going to thank you okay
you're gonna do some charitable work in
a Mexico
school you know you're going to spend
day after day and you're going to spend
all your money
and you're not going to sleep and you're
going to overwork for other people and
just get if you're in the buy serer
business forget getting thanks from
people if you're a good budy serer you
not only won't get thanks you'll get
criticism all day okay and tell them
off okay all right okay I'm
serious okay they're going to say oh
guess what didn't here I said I don't
care I'll serve you
too okay someone criticize you you're
like someone take all your money and
criticize you're like do you need
anything you know your reaction to these
people should be to serve them okay and
to help them that's a real buy Stu if
you're expecting people to thank you if
you think you're going to get praised
just forget it that's not the business
we're in okay that's not the business
we're in okay the Buddhist will pray for
you and the Buddhist will thank you that
should be enough okay you're not going
to get you you could get
really really serious uh criticism from
people and I think as a serious bodh
sappa you got to get used to it and you
can't be scared and you can't be wimy
you can't collapse every time someone
criticizes you as a bodh SAA you just
got to say thank you for your opinion
you know we're going to put you on hold
even though your Call's important to us
you
know and then just go away you know let
them stand there criticizing you and
you're already in the next state you
know and uh okay just relax you got to
learn to relax as a bu s okay
so uh m means in public online
probably UPA people will criticize you
they will troll troll you
troll they will troll do you say that
way do you say troll trolls will troll
you people will criticize you they by
the way they just want attention Okay
because they can't do anything
themselves so they it's easier to
criticize the people who are doing
something so just just laugh you know
okay thank you for your
opinion your troll is important to us
you know we'll be getting back to you
soon and and then turn it off and never
never write them back okay don't waste
your time with those people okay don't
waste your time don't even waste the
time to think about them like I have
this special Buddhist practice of
forgetting the names of people who
criticize me and I'm SU successful like
I swear I can't remember any of their
names okay because I don't think about
them okay so just relax helping people
business you're going to get criticized
and you know what are you gonna do
quit so just okay thank you your opinion
is important to
me don't get
irritated long means said don't get
pissed off okay don't don't take it
seriously okay those by the way all the
people who criticized me are
gone I don't even know where they are
they died they're
somewhere okay and then I they're just
gone okay and and if you live long
enough all the people who gave you
trouble will be
dead
and you know just keep going okay what
what else you going to do do are you
going to give up are you going to go
back to
Netflix you know what else you going to
do okay all
right uh here's a picture of storm
clouds this is weather in certain parts
of the country not here here is sunny
and nice all year
uh but there are places like
Japan during
Sakura when you pay four times the
normal Hotel rent to take your whole
family there to watch the cherry
blossoms open and they decide to wait
two
weeks and you go
home and on the way to the airport there
just opening
you right tell me that's what happened
this year Mr ARA was like I never saw
this happen G I
promise I'm sorry
thanks anyway uh the weather change
don't be like the weather okay don't be
like like Be steady don't be like
raining one minute and sunny the next
minute okay
loj Dharma practitioner You Got to Be
steady you can't be like this Koto
weather and Soto just by the way I'm not
complaining I'd still rather be in kot
okay but don't Don't Be Be steady okay
don't let little problems in your life
don't let especially
criticism don't don't I mean listen to
it if it makes any sense but since it
doesn't just let it go
okay all
[Music]
right when you help somebody
say Sid
Sid that's the Sanskrit okay that's the
famous line in the heart it's the only
line spoken by Buddha himself
Buddha uh uses two students like puppets
and has them have a conversation with
each other that's the whole heart Sutra
and when they finish giving This
brilliant teaching which is just
him he says oh so good so good okay it's
actually him talking right so lexo lexo
so lexo in colloquial
Tibetan became a word that means good
job
good job so in the heart Sutra Lord
Buddha says good job good job to the two
guys whose mouth he
controls okay and he says Rea means
don't help don't
hope that people are GNA come up to you
and say oh Le so you know thank you so
much you know you did such a good job on
the good night book club Lindsay you're
you're so wonderful thank you so much
it's not going to to happen Okay so
don't sit around waiting
for Le s okay don't sit around with it
for it in one way it's a lonely business
Dharma business is a lonely business
people are not going to you know come up
to you and say how wonderful you are but
that doesn't mean you shouldn't do it
right if you could if you're a surgeon
and you can save a
life what do you care if they ever see
you afterwards you know you saved
[Music]
okay then he starts on a subject called
Turning problems into
opportunities and I was studying all the
lojong of
History uh there's about a hundred major
lojong and and I just spent a couple
months studying all of them and um I was
trying to Define
what makes a loong a lojong and uh one
of the things you have to say is that
uh the theme of turning problems into
opportunities is through all the lojo
all the loong text all the LM texts they
have this one
theme that when a problem happens in
your life you should turn it around and
make a profit out of it okay and as a
business person
and we did make the largest diamond
jewelry company in the
world uh Warren Buffett bought it in
2009 uh this
skill of taking a problem and turning it
into a an opportunity is really really
cool it's really really uh useful okay
so it is a
Alm basic skill you know how to take
crap and turn it into gold you know how
to take a business
problem and make it into something
really fun and really amazing that's uh
that skill if you learn that larm Rim
skill it will serve you for the rest of
your life okay and and personal problems
too when you're having personal problems
with another person if you learn to
transform those
into opportunities
then every kind of crap that comes your
way becomes beautiful so the beautiful
stuff is already beautiful if the crap
becomes beautiful everything's beautiful
got it so if you have this magic
fingers who can take a problem and turn
it into
something really and I'm not
talking you take a problem and you learn
to live with it I'm not talking about
that I'm talking about you take a
problem and you learn to make a huge
profit from it uh that's really useful
that's really really useful and we're
going to cover it
tomorrow okay okay
[Applause]